[Music]
creatine is a compound formed naturally
in the human body that primarily
involved in energy production in our
muscles and brain it's also naturally
formed in the bodies of many animals we
eat and so when we eat their muscles we
can also take in some creatin through
our diet it was named after crus the
Greek word for meat in which it was
first isolated we need about 2 gam a day
so those we meet may get one gram from
their diet and their body makes the rest
from scratch there are rare birth
defects where you're born without the
ability to make it in which case you
have to get it all externally through
diet but otherwise our bodies can make
as much as we need to maintain normal
concentrations in our muscles when
people cut out meat the amount of
creatine floating around their
bloodstream goes down but the amount in
your brain Remains the Same because your
brain just makes all the creatine it
needs the level in vegetarian muscles is
lower but that doesn't seem seem to
affect performance as both vegetarians
and meteors respond to creatine
supplementation with similar increases
in muscle power output and if Vegetarian
Muscle creating was insufficient then
presumably they would have seen an even
bigger boost so basically when you eat
meat that just means your body doesn't
have to make as much if creatine muscle
content dropped As We Grew Older that
might help explain age- related muscle
loss but that doesn't seem to be the
case biopsies taken from the muscles of
young and old adults show no difference
in creating content still if it improves
performance maybe it would help
according to the international Society
of Sports Nutrition creatine monohydrate
is the single most effective ergogenic
supplement available to athletes for
increasing Exercise capacity and lean
body mass during training it's no wonder
surveys show as many as 70% plus College
athletes have used creatine supplements
what can it do for older
adults without exercise
nothing uh most studies on Creatine
supplementation alone show no benefits
for muscle mass strength or performance
this makes sense given the mechanism
creatine supplementation delays muscle
fatigue this enables people to work out
longer and harder and it's that
additional volume and intensity that
leads to the muscle benefits so creatine
alone doesn't help and creatine taken in
the context of the same training that's
carefully controlled and deliberately
equalized doesn't help either but let
people exercise as much as they can and
most studies on Creatine supplementation
for the prevention and treatment of
sarcopenia meaning age related muscle
loss show augmented lean mass as it does
in young adults adding 3 to 5 grams of
creatine a day to 2 to 3 days of
resistance training a week added an
additional three extra pounds of lean
mass over an average duration of about 4
months now some of that lean mass may be
water weight not muscle creatine causes
water retention that can show up as lean
mass but compared to Placebo creatine
combined with resistance exercise
increases muscle strength as well and
the additional gains in mass and
strength can persist as long as 12 weeks
after stopping the creatine and older
adults as long as the resistance
training is maintained so obviously it's
not all just water weight a reason I
never advocated for creatine
supplementation in older adults for
muscle preservation was because
systematic reviews up through 2017
concluded that adding creatine to
training shows mixed result results for
muscle mass and strength and it did not
appear to translate to improved
functioning however in updated
metaanalysis found a significant
improvement over Placebo in sitto Stand
test performance which is a decent
predictor of reduced Falls risk again
this was mostly only when accompanied by
strength training there have still been
no consistent benefits discovered for
just supplementing with creatine alone
so creatine should always be prescribed
with a progressive strength training
regimen the society for sarcopenia CIA
and wasting disease convened an expert
panel that despite the lack of long-term
trials suggested creatine be indeed used
for the management of
sarcopenia the recommended dose to
achieve muscle saturation is 3 gram a
day within a month at that slow steady
rate you achieve the same muscle levels
as loading with 120 gram over a period
of a week note though it takes at least
12 weeks of creatine supplemented
resistance training to see a significant
additive effect recent evidence suggests
taking it after exercise might be
slightly preferable to before but this
has yet to be verified are there any
side effects we'll find out next
[Music]